Finding Aid for George R. Fox (1880-1963) Papers 1915-1973 and undated
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George R. Fox papers 1915-1973, undated
Fox, George R., 1880-
1.5 linear feet
George R. Fox was an amateur Michigan archaeologist and author. His papers include writings about Cass County, Michigan, manuscripts related to archaeology and history, a small amount of correspondence, and photographs.
0383 Aa 2
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were transferred by the Museum of Anthropology (donor. no. 9273 ) in 2003.
The papers are open without restriction.
George Randall Fox was born in Peabody, Kansas on May 18, 1880 and grew up in Wisconsin. After completing high school, Fox worked for the post office for a number of years, but his great passions were archaeology and writing. Around 1900, he began collecting Native American artifacts and exploring various mounds and rivers in Wisconsin. In the ensuing years, Fox traveled to the southeastern United States, Mexico, and the Galapagos Islands in his spare time, in addition to participating in an expedition to Isle Royale (his report of which was published in The Wisconsin Archaeologist in 1911) to pursue his archaeological interests. Fox also authored a number of fiction and non-fiction manuscripts, most of which were never published.
In 1917 Mr. and Mrs. E.K. Warren asked Fox to serve for several months as the curator of a new museum they planned to establish in Three Oaks, Michigan called the Chamberlain Museum (the collections of the Chamberlain Museum later formed the basis of the Michigan State University Museum). After short stints at the Nebraska Historical Museum and back with the post office, he became the permanent curator several years later. In 1930, Fox left the museum to operate a camp for boys in Ontario for three years. He later moved to Cass County, worked for the city of Dowagiac, and founded a local historical society. Fox also wrote a column on Cass County local history for the Dowagiac Daily News and was a major contributor to The Acorn, another local paper.
Fox was active in several archaeological organizations, including the Michigan Archaeological Society and the Central States Branch of the American Anthropological Association. He contributed a number of archaeological reports and articles to publications such as The Wisconsin Archaeologist, Michigan History Magazine, and The Totem Pole (a publication of the Aboriginal Research Club of Detroit). Fox was honored several times for his contributions to amateur archaeology. In 1926 the Wisconsin Archaeological Society awarded him the Lapham Medal for "distinguished service in anthropological research." In 1960 the Michigan Archaeological Society gave him a distinguished service award.
Fox had three daughters and one son. Fox died on June 3, 1963 in Kalamazoo, Michigan.
The George R. Fox Papers are arranged in four series: Cass County, Archaeology and History Manuscripts, Correspondence, and Photographs. Many of the materials in the papers are undated.
Subjects:
Fox, George R., 1880-; Archaeology.; Cass County (Mich.)--History.; Michigan--Antiquities.; Mounds--Wisconsin.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Fox, George R., 1880-; Archaeology.; Mexico.; Michigan--Antiquities.; Mounds (Burials)--Wisconsin.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Cass County 1941-1973
  The Cass County series, 1941-1973 and undated (0.5 linear feet), contains notes and manuscripts Fox wrote on various topics related to Cass County history and archaeology. The "Cass County Archaeology" folders are the largest in the series, and include maps, drawings, and correspondence, in addition to Fox's writing. The "Cass County Historical Society" folder includes meeting minutes (some added after Fox's death by the holder of the papers) as well as a brief historical sketch of the society.
  - "A Man" (biography of Chief Leopold Pokagon) circa 1950 (Box 1)
  - "An Audit of the Scenic Historical and Recreational Facilities of Cass County and Dowagiac, Michigan," 1941 (Box 1)
  - Cass County Archaeology circa 1954-1955, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - "Cass County Courthouse," undated (Box 1)
  - Cass County Historical Society 1954-1973 (Box 1)
  - "Exploring," undated (Box 1)
    (includes photos)
  - "Indians in Cass County," undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscript on Ladies Library Association of Dowagiac 1950 (Box 1)
  - "Post Offices of Cass County," undated (Box 1)
  - "Resorts in Cass County," circa 1950 (Box 1)
  - "The Lost Grave" (re: location of Chief Leopold Pokagon's grave) undated (Box 1)
    (includes photo)
  - "The Magic That Is Cass County," circa 1958 (Box 1)
  - "The Postal System in Cass County," circa 1954 (Box 1)
  - "Too Much Water," 1954 (Box 1)
- Archaeology and History Manuscripts undated, 1928-1955
  The Archaeology and History Manuscripts series, 1928-1955 and undated (0.5 linear feet), contains a number of manuscripts Fox wrote on various topics related to archaeology and Michigan history (other than Cass County). Several concern the Griffin, a European ship that was lost on the Great Lakes in 1679.
  - "A New American Wonderland" (re: Berrien County, Michigan) undated (includes photos) (Box 1)
  - American Archaeology 1930s (Box 1)
  - "Archaeological Work on La Cloche Island," 1930 (Box 1)
  - "Discovery of a Skull in Jack County," circa 1938 (Box 1)
  - "Have the Remains of the Griffin Been Found?," undated (Box 1)
  - "La Salle's Ship, the Griffin and Its Pilot," undated (Box 1)
  - "Mammoth and Mastodon Remains in Berrien County," undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscript on Isle Royale Archaeology undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscript on James J. Strang undated (Box 1)
  - "Michigan's First Man," undated (Box 1)
  - "The First Great American Mystery," circa 1955 (Box 1)
  - "The Gulch Excavation" (Texas) undated (Box 1)
  - "The March That Began Chicago," undated (Box 1)
  - "The Mystery of the Effigy," 1928 (Box 1)
  - "The Mystery of the Griffin," undated (Box 1)
  - "The Recession Area of Southern Michigan," undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1915-1962
  The Correspondence series, 1915-1962 (5 folders), contains a small number of letters written by and to Fox. While its subjects include archaeology and publishing, the actual content is quite brief and sparse.
  - Allen, Durward 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - Archaeology 1952-1959 (Box 1)
  - Fiction and Publishers 1915-1941 (Box 1)
  - Mexico and Revillagigedo Islands 1923-1926 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1929-1962 (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1925-1928 (Box 2)
  The Photographs series, 1925-1928 and undated (0.5 linear feet), includes photographs of archaeological sites and artifacts, personal photographs of Fox and members of his family, and a photo album related to the Wisconsin Effigy Mounds. Most of the photos are unidentified as to subject and date.
  - Archaeology undated (Box 2)
  - Mexico 1925 (Box 2)
  - Personal undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Summerville Mound undated (Box 2)
  - Wisconsin Effigy Mounds 1928 (Box 2)
    (photo album)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 2)